hey everyone welcome
back it is September 26 2023 and we're
in cohort 4 meeting 14 on our second
discussion of chapter
six so before we jump over to the text
does anyone want to just give any
thought or take on
six
yeah briefly just Charles it's it
alternates time so the earlier time now
we're in cohort 4 chapter 6 and vice
versa but it's
all different angles on the same thing
so it's not like there's something that
won't make sense in six
because that's cool I'll just hang
around and
ab carry
on yeah so anyone want
to give a thought on six or we can look
at the questions that haven't been
addressed uh
yet
okay let's just go to a question and
then if somebody has another question
they can write in the chat or raise your
hand okay the authors talk about
language but in language processing one
usually assumes recursive processes egia
context free grammar how can Fe active
inference account for
recursivity in my understanding hidden
mark models Implement types of regular
grammars I assume that hierarchical
extensions I.E section 642 does not
fundamentally Chang this does
it did anyone here ask the question or
does anyone want to give a thought on
this
I'm not exactly sure what the question
is getting at however some senses of
recursion can be accommodated by
hierarchical
modeling so active inference models of
reading have for example letters nested
within words words nested within
sentences and so on so
this hierarchical model
embodies the
um the sparsity associated with this
kind of a recursive
process and then another kind of related
notion of recursion is closer to
re-entry where something is more like
self-reflexive and so that is less
referring to like the hierarchically
nested like kind of nested for Loops
notion and more having to do with like
re-entry of input and
reference which we might point to first
off just the fundamental
re-entry of the consequences of action
through
perception via the niche for the
agent and then a little bit more um on
the sophisticated cognitive entity the
recursive
identity concept and like identity
re-entering in reference to
itself Ali go for it
yeah well perhaps uh the question also
um I'm not sure but U maybe one angle to
answer this question is to answer
whether uh generative models are are
exclusively recursive models or not so
uh I believe uh in active inference
brain work and especially uh it's
current formulation there isn't any uh
restrictions for generative models to be
exclusively recursive so they can be
applied for both uh uh I mean nested and
recursive models and also in some
situations we can have um purely uh I
mean nonrecursive or sequential models
as well uh so uh yeah it it's in its
current standing it is much more broader
than uh only recursive kind of structure
as uh hhms were dealing with uh a couple
of decades
ago great point and it kind of returns
to the theme of chapter six and the
questions that are asked in chapter six
it's
like is or what what kind of recursive
phenomena is being desired to to be
modeled and
then there's sort of like what you
intentionally include in your model like
you know that you want to have this
phenomena and you're going to engineer
and and and um Implement motifs or
mechanics to get this phenomena like
it's your target phenomena you want to
have um a phase transition associated
with people like leaving a crowded room
and then like you want to like kind of
build that into the model super
explicitly and then a little bit more
indirectly would be you want to have
some phenomena
arising but you don't want that
phenomena to be like explicitly a
parameter in the
model
um but that's the chapter six question
what do you actually want to model what
system of interest do you want to model
and and that's
non-trivial to identify the boundaries
of the system and
to
subset what you actually want to model
about it and what's interesting what
questions you want to to
model
because otherwise you're just making a
map that's the
territory and there's no point in doing
so
okay how's the active inference modeling
recipe or approach to modeling similar
and different from other modeling
approaches that's a very good
question
just from what people have seen or what
they feel what's what's one or more
similarities or
differences whether people have have
done
[Music]
some quantitative
modeling like
statistics or systems engineering or
whether they've done some other informal
analysis
approach how is or could be active
inference chapter 6 recipe
different yeah
ali uh well I think this question um is
I don't know perhaps too General uh to
be answered um sufficiently or helpfully
but um when it comes to active inference
modeling my own understanding is that uh
the main thing that sets it apart from
uh perhaps all the other or many other
approaches uh is um its emphasis on
constructing uh the useful and
appropriate generative model
so uh in all the other approaches
uh the representation of the world or
the phenomena uh we're trying to model
is not something uh
that it's not on uh very clear uh
probabilistic representation terms uh so
to speak but in active inference uh
there is this clear distinction between
what ex what kind of phenomena or uh
What uh maybe we can say what kind of
structure uh the phenomena or um uh the
the system we're trying to model
encapsulates in terms of Its
probabilistic Behavior Uh so uh it is
much more clearer than other modeling
approaches uh when it comes to the
representation uh of that a specific
system world or uh the phenomena of
interest uh uh
in relation to its generative model
construction so yeah I think the main
distinction uh lies exactly in uh the
approach to constructing that
representation thanks any anyone else
feel free to raise your hand or go for
it I I'll also point to recent work by
Ma at all from
this
year where they uh well designing
explainable artificial intelligence with
active inference a framework for
transparent introspection and
decisionmaking it points towards some of
the
motifs that make it different and which
give it a semantic
interpretability because when features
of the system including its own
introspection its own confidence on its
answers or its sense making are framed
in terms of probabilistic
parameters that that are just what it
says on the
label then there is a clear sense of
what structure or phenomena arising from
structure of the system that we're
modeling that doesn't mean that the
model in hand is going to be
the system we're modeling obviously
that's the whole map territory fallacy
map territory fallacy
fallacy
situation but when we
have um interpretable
parameters that play explicit roles in
semantic basian
networks then
um at least we're on that path yeah I'll
I'll
[Music]
um I'll bring that paper into I don't
I'm sure it's somewhere else in in here
but um Charles this is
the paper of uh ramstead at all on the
map territory fallacy
fallacy and just in brief commonly
people talk about map territory fallacy
which would be the fallacious equip
equence of a map in a
territory people are pretty familiar
with map territory fallacy map is not
the territory all that you know maps are
useful some are all of
that and in this paper they point to a
kind
of extreme
case where people will look at active
inference free energy principle modeling
and say oh well it's just making a map
so it's it's just making a map of the
territory so it's not the territory so
it's kind of like what's what's the
issue like what what's the value
at um and
so uh there's a few aspects to
this and uh it relates to on one
side um
reification of the map and the territory
like you go with the map to the
territory and then like you you you know
that it's that the map's not the
territory yet still they are used to
kind of co- justify each other and then
another flavor is oh well then free
energy principle does nothing if it's
just helping us build
Maps that's nothing that's just a
mapping framework and that's
like a fallacy on the map territory
fallacy OE or or anyone else what what
what other angles are there I I can
actually just chime in quickly because
it relates to the one or sort of
two-part question comment that I did put
inota last week um relating to chapter
one but it had it maybe it's a Sim
another angle on the same thing which is
the modeling versus action it's kind of
a can of worms but I don't know if you
if that's enough of a prompt to kind of
address these terms yeah how do you see
it well I I'm not sure this is just was
my one of my initial questions that came
up right away um
where I guess the answer is in the
definitions but but in practice how is
the modeling modeling as
action compared to modeling in contrast
to action I guess that's the best I can
put it right
now that's very interesting
like modeling is an action it's an
iterated process that a modeler takes in
fact we could even do a chapter six on
chapter six and make a cognitive model
of somebody applying active inference to
modeling eventually I expect that that
would be relevant so there is a sense in
which modeling is an action it's a
practice it has explicit and implicit
skill associated with it so modeling is
action however
modeling throwing a baseball isn't
throwing a
baseball there there's a tiny bit more I
can add which I I see I had written also
I think in Koda um under Cod word five
of of course observing and documenting
are both also action however the systems
and be behaviors being observed Obed
would be the primary actors in the sense
of the
action uh yeah anyway it has to do with
that observing as action is relates to
that
too thank you yeah we'll we'll
um return to these but but um think
about the setting of of so let's just
say we're chapter sixing a baseball game
so we have a person who's a spectator
they are still taking action with their
iade to look at different parts of the
field reducing their
uncertainty and then covertly
internally they are deploying attention
as
action attending to different parts of
their
experience so even
a seemingly passive perhaps overtly
passive Observer
is active at least in the attentional
covert internal sense if not also in the
epistemic
foraging
icade sense like choosing where to
look but none of that activity happening
in The
Spectator is the
action happening on the
field and then to connect this back to
the map territory fallacy fallacy no
matter how deep we go into this um model
of like a spectator and an
athlete it does the end of the process
isn't going to be like a material
spectator and an
athlete the map of that setting that
cognitive setting isn't the
territory that's so so now now now we're
immune to the map territory fallacy map
is not the territory but then what is it
it's a map and then um I I'll also note
that that ramstead and Sak devel and
friston go a little bit
further than um just
naming their
critique of this
deployment they come back even stronger
and
say actually free energy principle is
the ideal
model and any model that doesn't
conform to the free energy principle
with respect to the map territory
scenario is either saying too much or
too little
Oli uh so there's this heated debate in
uh the philosophy of mind and um I don't
know the philosophy of Neuroscience
about a mological
fallacy um which uh says something to
the effect that uh it is a fallacy to
ascribe uh a psychological action to a
part of a cognitive agent uh so when we
say that uh the brain does something
it's not actually what brain uh that
does that specific action but uh the
whole agent that uh possess U uh the
brain is responsible for the action so
uh I'm not sure uh
how I mean in this kind of self
referential uh scenario of modeling uh
this mological
fallacy uh holds or not or whether at
what point uh we can uh escape this
mological fallacy but uh when it comes
to uh map territory fallacy fallacy my
understanding is that the F and active
inference escape this exact mological
fallacy right from the beginning by not
uh uh conflating map uh and the
territory and uh or in other words by
taking a totally different approach to
the concept of
agency uh uh
and it's not something that
just
metaphorically uh ascribed to part of
the system so uh when they say that uh a
part of a system looks as if it does
some kind of inference or um any action
uh it's not just a pure metaphor it's uh
built into uh the very fabric of active
inference Theory so uh yeah yeah I
believe in that case uh this kind of
self referential scenario can be applied
indefinitely if you wanted to with uh
this specific kind of
approach thank you Ali
I'll see if this is kind of another
piece of it when we say a system looks
as if it is bounding surprise or it's
reducing
surprise that's not
metaphorical or the realist Claim about
the
territory it's a
narrow and limited Claim about the
map which and and now all claims about
Maps unless they're being considered in
some abstract mapping setting are on the
foundation of the relationship between
the map and the
territory
how is it being approached differently
in
actim we have
figure
9.2
9.1 the metab basian so here in the
center we have the cognitive model of
the system of interest of the subject of
mod the modeling subject and then
outside of the subject object is the the
this is figure and
ground so we're being explicit that
we're making a map about the cognitive
about the cognitive model of the subject
now that subject's cognitive model could
be a map of the environment as well but
once we enter into
this mode of
modeling we're
not making claims
about the
subject we're either making claims about
our map of the
subject and then a subset of that is
maps that the subject makes makes about
the
environment I hope that didn't say too
much or too
little but I think that is what what
what it resonates in me when when Al say
is what we kind of
head off that fallacy from the
beginning because the task that we're
doing in cognitive modeling if this is a
rat in a teamas or if this is some you
know digital environment or something
like that is we set up our work
explicitly as making a
map rather than like well what does the
amydala
do it's like well then you're going to
get into a situation like are we making
claims about the amydala because that's
a claim about the
territory but if we say well we're
building a map of the
Amiga and one of the functionalities in
our map is that the Amiga is making a
map of its
environment so that's a kind of nested
mapping and that's this that may related
to the earlier recursion question but
now if we have
um pre prevented or styed off this map
territory fallacy which is actually
fairly easy to identify if it's
approached
hygienically then
we're just not making claims
about the amygdala
directly we're building the
map which can include
submaps but then there doesn't have to
be I I mean this is the uh the the Sila
in the cibus map territory fallacy on
one hand and then the fallacy fallacy on
the other
hands because like the map's utility in
relevance is related to it's its
mapping of
course which we we want to be able to
say things like yeah Fourth Street and
Fifth Street Run in parallel and I'm not
just talking about my
map but that that's the empirical
question
um I had a question about the map and
territory could you explain uh more
about what the fallacy
is yeah I I'll give it first take
broadly the map territory
fallacy is
when a constructed map which is to say
an abstraction or a model of some
real material system of Interest or
territory when especially in a science
or research or modeling setting it can
be easy to kind of conflate or use
rhetoric from one regarding the other so
we have a bunch of healthcare data on
you know doing this and this health
outcome and we did a linear regression
and we found that smoking was increasing
the risk of lung cancer sounds like a
relevant thing to say but the more
narrow statistical claim would
be there was a statistically significant
positive regression slope between this
measure and that
measure so that's on the mapping we did
a linear aggression and we want to be
able I mean it's like look at the line
don't we want to be able to say that
there's like a positive relationship
between these things in the real world
so that's the tension because you'd want
to be able to just first off look at
your statistical results on the map and
make a statement about the territory
like doing this increases
that
um but that's already leaving the map
it's like you're looking at the map it's
like well it looks like these two roads
intersect um at this GPS coordinate but
it's like but that doesn't mean that
they do especially if you're like
extrapolating
so so then if somebody were to have
smoked twice as much then they would
have this much
more so the map territory fallacy is
just it's done in science communication
it's done in selft talk it's done in so
many different
settings
where something is gleaned or
constructed in the map as all maps are
and then that is used to justify and
sometimes even linguistically is is
woven or completely mixed into claims
about the
territory which may be valid or aligned
or resonant or like pointing in the same
direction so it's not like we're not in
a situation where like maps are like
deceptive unless they are
but that is the
tension what can you say about
the map and the territory but it starts
with just the fundamental recognition
and and the repeated exhortation that
the map's not the territory which is why
you hear that as well as like all models
are wrong some are useful or the borest
story of the the map maker who like
makes a map that's so detailed that it
covers everything and then like it
becomes the
territory those are all kind of
allegorical ways to talk about it but
the big issue is when we're doing
scientific modeling we're doing map
making and there's this complexity of
relationship between any map and any
territory and again it would be so
simple and straightforward to just make
the map do the statistics and then the
statistics should just apply right back
to the
territory you know I have GPS locations
on these two objects I made a
statistical model of their location in
the statistical model they are close so
can we say that the objects are close
it's like just let me say
that but if it were that way yeah
exactly as Charles says it's not so
clean distinct there are settings where
it is clean and
distinct but those are not every
setting that makes
sense and it happens a ton in
Neuroscience as well
because the territory is so messy and
ineffable that it's like somebody will
make
some list of terms or they'll make some
axes that they're studying summary
statistics or um personality traits or
just somebody brings some framework to
to reckon or to grasp with Neuroscience
or with psychology
and then they start reifying the
existence it's like I can't believe
there's things in the upper left
quadrant of this thing that I made but
that's again it's a statement of maps on
territories um aith or oi sorry go
ahead uh yeah I just wanted to mention
uh a probably useful distinction made by
uh delus between representation and uh
cartography so uh he makes a clear
distinction between what we want to
represent in other words uh what we want
to trace uh in our models and uh the
cartography or uh the action of mapping
uh something in the model or diagramming
or metam modeling or whatever uh so uh
in this sense uh I think what active
inference does uh I mean in light of
this distinction between representation
and cartography um more maps into uh the
representation uh side of modeling uh in
other words uh the very active
constructing a generative model uh of
the of the world or the phenomenon
phenomenon of interest is done by
tracing uh the probabilistic states uh
of the world so it's not cartography in
the sense of mapping or diagramming or
met modeling but rather it actually does
uh this very active tracing or
representation so uh I think it also
helps to uh distinguish between uh the
usual way of uh talking about mapping or
modeling in other scientific Endeavors
and uh the active inference way of doing
things
would there ever be a case where you are
talking about the territory like I'm
just kind of wondering like when you
would ever talk about the territory and
science because wouldn't it always be
sort of some representation you're
working
with what do you
think
olly yeah so uh it depends on what um
what we mean by um representation in
relation to the territory we're trying
to quote unquote
represent uh but u i mean even the
simplest Act of observing the world and
um I mean observing anything that we
want to model uh entails
uh at least uh an elementary uh kind of
um representation or cartography combin
combined so uh maybe uh I mean it's not
possible theoretically and
philosophically even to uh have a direct
access
uh to the territory we want to study but
the only way we can um we can have
anything useful to say about uh that
specific territory is through the
representation in
cartography um at least this is uh one
of the um views hold held by um
structural
realists uh and specifically ontological
structural realists so it's
not uh it's not about the content of the
world but the structure uh a structure
of the the content of that world uh
manifests themselves that scientists are
interested in uh so yeah at least in in
some uh
perspectives it's not possible to have
that direct knowledge of the territory
I think it's an excellent question as
many we just kind of surfac them and
it's for people to consider but
but if we were engineers and if we were
building a bridge and we had the
blueprint and we were talking about the
blueprint like is it sufficient to just
make strong claims about blueprints that
we have in hand on the table and
then understand that there's a Rel
relationship between the blueprints that
we make and the territory that we care
about is that enough like is that like a
firewalled approach we're we're only
going to talk about the blueprint that
we have on the table and blueprints are
related to
Bridges or are there times where we want
to bypass the
blueprint and just say um you know maybe
look at the bridge and say these two
things look like they're this way um and
then yeah what do you think about
this yeah like I guess there are some
cases where you'd have to make sure you
know that they're distinct
um especially like when you're
considering the things the blueprint
can't really capture about the
bridge yeah and in in neuro and
psychology these these come up
especially like when classifying brain
regions or when classifying um different
neurod
diversities one topic um that that Ali's
mentioned of the
traces in the world this reminded me of
Bruno Lor's work on actor Network Theory
and ants and this is a very like Proto
active
approach it's all about resuming the
task of
tracing and it's it's very provocative
and another um I think provocative
philosophical um term in this uh space
is always already think like these are
just two English words come on
now the perception of phenomena by the
mind of an observer the features of
phenomena that seem to precede any
perception of it are said to be always
already
present
that is
very provocative I
believe or evocative it's
like it was already that
way
so we're showing up in the Stream of
things potentially resuming the
tracing of
associativity in a map making
setting Charles quick context definition
of blueprint and
Bridge there I was being completely
exoteric I really was talking about a
civil
engineering setting with people
sketching out a
blueprint like an architectural grounds
plan about a bridge that like cars would
drive
over so compared to the actual bridge
then yeah and then the neuroscience
setting you know we'd have we have the
person's body is the
territory okay cool and then yeah and
then the blueprint would be some some
you know chapter 5 like well here's how
you know the elbow bonees connected to
the knee
bone but the body
is a complex territory which is why so
much has been written and explored on it
indeed thank you
yeah the body's a bridge too right sorry
go ahead and the body's a bridge and the
body's body as map body as void you know
this as that this already always as that
like that's that's the
fun um okay let's go to this question
from
Andrew okay selft talk is one of the
topics or activities where map territory
concerns apply any direct work or paper
references on this topic you could
share H what do people
think and yeah just to to chime in I
mean I I just heard you say that along
the way whenever we were um discussing
the policy there and it just really
piqued my interest so um but uh I mean I
can already imagine how that could play
out as far as someone considering you
know the themselves the cognitive
process of like they're attempting to
map whatever it is that's going on with
them whatever it is they're directing
their attention towards versus the
territory that is entire generative
process going on that that probably from
an active inference framework they're
only going to be able to kind of
approximate in their own model of that
territory but in any case I just um so
uh feel like I could get into an
infinite regress here with just thinking
of what's going on whenever I selft talk
and uh was curious if there was any
published work here or um anything along
those
lines I don't know of
any
published work on this I'm sure there
are analyses on like self-reported
self-talk but it's something that is
understandably hard to
measure in flow and you get into all
these kind of like
recursive questions what if you
remembered saying it to yourself but you
didn't in the moment or you did say it
in the moment but you didn't remember it
or tend to it
um yeah I I mentioned it just because it
is like the kind
of
Singularity of map and
territory like okay let's just say that
the that a cognitive
activity is making Maps so um just you
know putting ourselves in the driver's
seat not figure 9.1 not behavioral
researcher but you could take that
stands to but View From the
Inside we are making maps of our ter you
know where OB objects are in the room
and all these other
things and then
that map
reenters
through her
language and sub vocalized language so
it is embodied action as well
a so by selft talk do you mean like an
inner monologue um I think I might be
missing some context yeah yeah like
stream of
Consciousness whether thing just the the
internal flow in
imagination or even explicit self-
coaching uh I've seen a paper published
where they use like fmri data to predict
what people's inner monologues are if
that might be
something that could be some way of
mapping out this
territory um also what people are sort
of imagining visually and also what
they're listening like what they're
perceiving in terms of
Music things like
that um I think like the latest sort of
deep learning models are actually
getting sophisticated enough where they
can be able to predict what people are
intuiting just using like the right type
of
data just to say that that very much is
in line with the kind of thing I'd be
interested in uh I guess bonus points
that I'm interested in neuroimaging
data especially so um I just shared is
is this um I can send some papers
that actually yeah put them in here just
follow the little token and then add
them in
here oh I I just shared one just to see
if I could confirm with you is is this
at
all in line with what you were referring
to there
a uh is it on the screen oh yeah yeah
that is uh P FM
[Music]
D um just
a quick Google search not trying to
throw us off track
here uh this is not the one I was
referring to but I can find the one I
was referring to I think it was like
recent it was like in
2023 oh that even better right great I
really appreciate it thank
you
wow yeah it's this is very I mean and to
kind of return to chapter six like this
is why we have a chapter six this is why
unified approaches to perception
cognition action matter this is why
having an active inference
ontology is important this is why having
a
recipe
for making generative
models and having some of this meta
Theory or meta
position on the relationship of map and
territory fallacy and fallacy fallacy
and fallacy cubed
um because these are not
just massively interactive and nonlinear
systems of
Interest they're also ones that were
always already
experiencing so if it was just
a rubbe Goldberg
machine that would be one
thing but it's still wouldn't even be of
the
type
qualitatively of without even going too
deep into phenomenology and like
experience and
awareness it just wouldn't necessarily
be of the
type that would be a recursive
re-entrant cognitive
system and this is why
um I think the textbook
ends
with these
lines important rights of Passage in
theoretical
neurobiology are trying to write down a
generative model experiencing the
frustration when simulations misbehave
and learning from violations of your
prior belief when something unexpected
happens
so it's
like this isn't just a hot take like
there's you what can you say about some
of these settings that's just like oh
okay it's it's it's you don't just
like drop the mic and like dust off your
hands in this iterated generative
modeling
practice it's
like especially if we're
applying it to a setting like selft talk
let's say or some other psychological
phenomena um which you know impinges or
overlaps on selft talk
um you write down the generative
model there's a recipe it's chapter six
plus some of the other pieces that
people have added in you write it
down you roll it
out you see what happens did you expect
what happens
well if you understand act in and you
made a simple example you may have you
may expect get exactly what you expect
back like well I made it I made an
oscillating
pendulum and it it did exactly that it's
like great well that that might be like
a homework assignment for
like a certain
course but if we're interested in
something with more richness than like a
pendulum then when we unroll that
generative
model we will be
surprised and then what do we do with
surprise well we know there's two ways
to bound it change mind change the world
change your mind learn an update change
the world re-enter change the generative
model itself on the
table so having a
structured approach profession ontology
methodology toolkit etc etc comes into
play and chapter six is kind of
the transition point or like the fulcrum
that the book is actually organized
around chapters 1 through three get us
to active
inference context low road high road to
or
of chapter 4
generative
modelss chapter 5 generative models in
the Maman Neuroscience
setting and then pretty much as soon as
we can chapter six now it's us making
that generative
model
and even without extensive math or
programming
experience we can start to address some
of these questions
and then we're
already in the flow of
things it can definitely feel like
chapter 4 is
like well chapters two and three can
feel like waiting through like every
single Department of learn
in just to get
two and then chapter 4 can feel like
getting
through is
like impossible slash
improbable
all totally make sense in terms of their
evaluation and how they're
experienced but then like we break out
on the other side of four just from a
page Turner
perspective in
six and this is like such an incredible
open conversation about
modeling and these qu they're hard
questions to talk about
but hopefully people can see that at the
single entity or at the research group
group
scale having alignment or
shared reference
frames around some of these
topics are make or
break
thanks ath you can add just just you
know add make little sub Pages or add
your own question or just you know just
just the more references and the more
things people add the better it's
awesome okay yeah I can do that thank
you one other piece I'll just add on
this kind of map territory is the the
digital
introduces a very interesting setting
that's kind of like a chessboard in the
sense that it's fully
observable and that these are
virtualized
settings
where strong concordances between maps
and
territories can be constructed to
exist
so like there can be a schema an
abstract pattern or
[Music]
scheme that
then generates the
territory in a we know ultimately it's
embodied through like thermodynamics and
information all this so so not but but
to a first
approximation the digital
systems have a different map territory
relationship
than
Birds
to the inner talk Point body's eye this
just made me think like inner talk is is
re-entrance
auditory action and perception even
though it doesn't go through the
ear I assume that these um Imaging
studies ask the question maybe even find
the result that there's like activation
of of auditory processing or something
like that um
then we have
visual but these are so those are
[Music]
um internalized exteroceptive processes
inner eye inner ear inner
touch but then like do we have
internalized
interceptive as well like can we take an
inner virtual view on something that's
already
inner and and is that you
know different where is it more or less
relevant than selft
talk but if you could take an inner
position on the interpretation of the
selft
talk then I think we get into Andrew's
infinite
regresses yeah I don't know it just
brings up so many questions for me of
how to conceptualize that one because I
mean in in a certain way if someone were
to engage in selft talk I could view it
is like
they're if we view the self itself as
like a kind of M map that the the person
has constructed so you're you're you
you've taken your map and and now you're
making a map of your map perhaps like
analyzing it or maybe you're just
engaging in some kind of nested
structure learning like oh let me revise
my model of myself I I don't know
there's so
many I think a you know some kind of
more empirical work would need something
a little bit more finessed than the way
I'm talking about it right now but it's
they interesting ways it could go I
could imagine
know yeah
like the system can't a a system cannot
just
provide if it if it just represents
everything then it's just a pass through
system there's no
attention or distillation or
representation just a straight pass
through so whether we're talking about
ourselves or some other hypothetical
system the self-representation that it
explicitly makes to itself is a sample
or a selection or an attention
distribute reallocation of something
else like that's just like kind of light
and
dark like I is it all equally lit and
just a pass through or is there going to
be some area that is brought more into
focus
[Music]
in the
representation and then so what should
be
represented maybe that's where people
have different um views obviously but
there's the preference to have our
representation be amicable or like
Pleasant that's clearly one drive
another Drive is for
meaning all these different
things and I think you recall somewhere
earlier in the textbook uh first will
the author say something about a a an
agent having a model of itself in order
to differentiate itself from its
environment I.E the generative process
around it and how that may be an
essential
possibly an essential aspect at least
for certain entities in maintaining
something along the lines of homeostasis
that is if you don't have a sense of
what you need and what you need to do
which is part of you then then
potentially you dissipate you know into
the entropic uh processes around you so
anyway I don't want to keep but
interesting
yeah it's fun yeah as as usual another
great um chapter six Journey chap
chapter six is is like an inflection
point in the bur and and in how we
approach things so we will then in the
coming weeks with the alternating times
head into chapter seven and eight on
discreet and continuous time
models chapter nine on datab based
analysis chapter 10 wrapping things up
all right thanks
everyone till next
time you bye